Guide to the John Tabor Kempe Papers 1678-1782 (bulk 1752-1774) MS 344
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
John Tabor Kempe Papers
1678-1782 (bulk 1752-1774)
MS 344
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
7.5 Linear feet
The John Tabor Kempe Papers contain primarily court case records (12 boxes) for the colonial province of New York during the tenures of Attorneys General William Kempe and his son, John Tabor Kempe. The bulk of these records date from 1752 to 1774, and concern civil disputes, often over land ownership, tenancy and estates, as well as criminal acts. Also included in the papers are professional correspondences of both John Tabor Kempe and William Kempe, court agendas and fees, legal papers, land and property records, financial records, government documents, and a photograph.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Separated Materials
BV NYS -- Boundaries -- Oblong; two boxes of papers pertaining to the Oblong dispute.
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
The Alexander Papers, 1668-1818 (bulk 1717-1786), which also contain colonial court records.
Arrangement
The John Tabor Kempe Papers are organized into the following seven series:
Series 1: Court Case Records, 1678-1778 (bulk 1752-1774), and Undated
Series 2: Correspondence, 1730-1775 (bulk 1753-1774), and Undated
Series 3: Legal Papers, 1760-1782 and Undated
Series 4: Land and Property Records, 1742-1775 and Undated
Series 5: Financial Records, 1718-1775 and Undated
Series 6: Government Records, 1722-1773 and Undated
Series 7: Photograph, Undated
Scope and Contents note
The John Tabor Kempe Papers contain primarily court case records (12 boxes) for the colonial province of New York during the tenures of Attorneys General William Kempe and his son, John Tabor Kempe. The bulk of these records date from 1752 to 1774, and concern civil disputes, often over land ownership, tenancy and estates, as well as criminal acts. Offenses range from minor assaults and infractions to capital crimes, including murder and high treason. A separate database exists for the court case records in this collection, containing over 750 entries.
Also included in the papers are professional correspondences of both John Tabor and William Kempe, court agendas and fees, legal papers, land and property records, financial records, government documents, and a photograph.
While a number of well-known legal cases are represented in this collection (i.e. The King vs. Alexander McDougall), the John Tabor Kempe Papers also support research in the lives of ordinary colonial New Yorkers, many of whom are otherwise undocumented. Records also detail numerous land conflicts that erupted in the decades prior to the Revolutionary War, including riots and intrusion cases in the counties, and territorial disputes with Native Americans and with neighboring colonies, especially Connecticut and New Hampshire. Historians of colonial law will find a variety of cases and legal documents in this collection, and John Tabor Kempe's trial notes and correspondence provide insight into a prominent eighteenth-century legal mind.
This collection contains mostly professional records, with very little personal material for either John Tabor Kempe or William Kempe.
Biographical Note
1752 Nov. William Kempe appointed Attorney General for the Province of New York
1759 July/Aug. William Kempe dies; his son, John Tabor Kempe, is appointed Attorney General for the Province of New York
1766 John Tabor Kempe marries Grace Coxe
1767 John Tabor Kempe travels to England; James Duane serves as acting Attorney General in his absence
1768 John Tabor Kempe resumes position, is re-appointed
1777 John Tabor Kempe's tenure as Attorney General ends
1783 John Tabor Kempe returns to England, makes Loyalist land claims
1791 John Tabor Kempe dies in England
Bleecker, Rutger; Bradstreet, John, 1711-1774; Chase, Henry; Cock, Ann; Cockburn, Will; Congregation Shearith Israel (New York, N.Y.).; Duncan, John; Dysart, Richard; Gomez, Daniel; Hausbrouck, Abraham; Hays, Solomon; Hayward, Sarah; Hicks, Whitehead, 1728-1780; Johnson, William, Sir, 1715-1774; Kempe, William, d. 1759; Klock, George; Lydius, John Henry, 1694-1791; New York (State). Attorney General's Office.; New York (State). Court of Chancery.; New York (State). Court of General Sessions of the Peace (New York County).; New York (State). Court of Oyer and Terminer (New York County).; New York (State). Court of Vice Admiralty.; New York (State). Mayor's Court (New York).; New York (State). Supreme Court.; Nimham, Daniel; Schuyler, Harmanus; Silvester, Peter; Spencer, George; Swords, Thomas; Wetherhead, John; Yates, Abraham, 1724-1796; Accounts; Affidavits; Assault and battery -- New York (State); Attorneys general; Bonds (legal records); Briefs (legal documents); Civil court records; Correspondence; Costs (Law) -- New York (State); Counterfeits and counterfeiting -- New York (State); Courts -- New York (State); Courts -- New York (State) -- New York; Criminal court records; Daguerreotypes (photographs); Decedents' estates -- New York (State); Deeds; Depositions; Ejectment -- New York (State); Estate records; Extinguishment of Indian title -- New York (State) -- Dutchess County; Indians Of North America -- Land tenure -- New York (State) -- Dutchess County; Jews -- New York (State) -- New York; Justice, Administration of -- New York (State); Land grants; Landlord and tenant -- New York (State); Larceny -- New York (State); Law -- New York (State); Lawyers; Lawyers -- Fees -- New York (State); Legal correspondence; Legal documents; Legal instruments; Legal notices; Libel and slander -- New York (State); Memorandums.; Murder -- New York (State); New Hampshire -- Boundaries -- New York (State); New York (State) -- Boundaries; New York (State) -- Boundaries -- New Hampshire; New York (State) -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; New York (State) -- History -- French and Indian War, 1755-1763; Oblong Tract (N.Y.); Petitions; Practice of law -- New York (State); Prisoners -- New York (State); Prostitution -- New York (State); Rape -- New York (State); Real property -- New York (State); Riots -- New York (State); Subpoenas; Trading with the enemy; Treason -- New York (State); Trespass -- New York (State); Trespass--New York (State); Trials -- New York (State); Trover and conversion -- New York (State); Wappinger Indians; Wills
- Series 1: Court Case Records, 1678-1778 (bulk 1752-1774), and Undated, 1678-1778 and Undated
  Scope and Contents note
  The bulk of the court case records in this collection are for cases argued in the New York Supreme Court of Judicature. Other courts include the Court of Chancery, Court of Vice-Admiralty, New York General Sessions (in counties), New York General Quarter Sessions (in New York City), Court of Mayor and Aldermen, and the Court of Oyer and Terminer. Cases argued before the Governor and Council are also found in this series.
  Court case records are arranged by the court in which a case was argued. Within each court, cases are divided into criminal and civil, then arranged alphabetically by defendant for criminal cases, by plaintiff for civil cases. Cases with multiple plaintiffs or defendants are filed under the first name to appear on the documents. In addition, this series includes documents for cases for which the court, plaintiff or defendant cannot be determined. Cases where the court venue is unclear, but plaintiff and defendant are evident, are filed under "Court Undetermined." Documents that are most likely related to a court case, but the court, plaintiff, and/or defendant cannot be determined are filed under "Case Undetermined." Many of these undetermined cases are represented by a single document.
  Court case documents include briefs, presentments, affidavits, trial notes, complaints, statements of cases, indictments, memoranda, subpoenas, pleas, notices, depositions, rules, certiorari, narratios, replications, bail notices, trial notices, notes, petitions, jury lists, costs, and other relevant documents such as estate records or accounts. Many items are drafts or contemporary copies. Petitions not linked to any specific case are filed together within Case Undetermined.
  All cases in this series have been entered into a separate database. The database information generally includes court, location, dates, items, plaintiff and defendant, and charge or suit for each case. A notes field also contains other pertinent information about the case, such as references to other relevant cases and correspondence. (Correspondence that was filed with individual court cases has been removed to Series II, and each item removed is listed in the notes field--additional correspondence not listed may also relate to specific court cases, as many letters were already filed separately). A complete report derived from this database is available for researchers, sorted by court. A separate report sorted by charge/suit is also available. The database can be searched by name or keyword--see Manuscript Department staff.
  This collection also includes numerous land tenant ejectment cases. These suits were brought on the behalf of a fictitious current tenant, usually called "James Jackson," though other names were also used ("Peter Quiet," "John Denn"). Therefore, ejectment cases are filed by the first plaintiff to follow the fictitious name. The false names "John Stiles" and "John Turnout" were commonly used for defendants.
  Political cases represented in this series include King vs. Alexander McDougall in the Supreme Court of Judicature for libel/slander, several trading with the enemy cases during the French and Indian War (especially the various George Spencer cases in the Supreme Court of Judicature and the Court of Vice-Admiralty), and a number of cases involving maladministration of Justices of the Peace.
  Court case records also document the quotidian disputes of New Yorkers, particularly in assault cases, and sometimes reveal contentious relationships between men and women, masters and servants, ministers and their congregations, and neighbors. Women are present throughout the series as both plaintiffs and defendants, and a few cases include unkept marriage promises, and accusations of rape. Many cases involve disputes within religious institutions, particularly the Protestant Dutch Church. The King vs. Nepthali Hart Meyers, Hayman Levi, Daniel Gomez et al in the Supreme Court of Judicature details a violent disagreement within a NYC synagogue.
  Several cases in this collection involve the accusation of slaves for various crimes; see King vs. Belinda, King vs. Venus, King vs. Falmouth, King vs. Pompey, in the Supreme Court of Judicature and King vs. Abraham, King vs. Scipio in Court Undetermined. A number of cases concern slaves seeking their freedom, often claiming false enslavement in the American colonies; see Juan Miranda vs. Cornelius and Sarah Van Ranst in the Supreme Court of Judicature, the case of Francis de Salas Cortilla in Governor and Council, and the cases of Vacan Beneto (petition), Simon Moore, Jacob Quaco, and the estate of William West, all in Case Undetermined.
  In some instances, the court in which a case was argued was determined through the use of an outside source, especially Julius Goebel Jr. & T. Raymond Naughton's Law Enforcement in Colonial New York: A Study in Criminal Procedure (1664-1776) (NY: The Commonwealth Fund, 1944). Daniel Allen Hearn's Legal Executions in New York State, 1639-1963 (N.C.: McFarland & Co., 1997) was also consulted. Both are referenced in the note field of the database when applicable. Further information on many cases in the collection can also be found in these sources.
  Note: Many cases contain alternate spellings for the names of plaintiffs and defendants. The most common was used for indexing; alternate spellings are also included in brackets. A number of documents contain the abbreviation "ads," i.e. John Smith ads. William Thomas. With this abbreviation, the defendant is listed first and the plaintiff listed second, rather than the more common Thomas vs. Smith, or Thomas agt. Smith. Other abbreviations found in the collection are "ex dem" meaning "upon the demise" (used in ejectment cases) and "qui tam" meaning the plaintiff has launched a civil suit on behalf of the state.
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Criminal, A-B (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Criminal, C (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Criminal, D (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Criminal, E-G (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Criminal, H (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Criminal, J-K (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Criminal, L (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Criminal, Lydius (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Criminal, M-N (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Criminal, O-R (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Criminal, S-T (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Criminal, U-Z (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Criminal, Van Renselaer (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, A (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, Ba-Bri (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, Bro-Bu (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, Ca-Co (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, Cr-Cu (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, Da (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, De-Dy (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, E (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, Fa-Fo (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, Fr-Fu (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, G (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, Ha (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, Hardenbrook vs. Bogert (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, He-Hy (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, J (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, K (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, Kempe vs. [ ...? ] (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, La-Leake (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, Lefferts-Lo (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, M (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, N-P (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, Ra (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, Re-Ru (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, Sc (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, Se-Si (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, Sm-Sp (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, St (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, Swords (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, Ta-Ti (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, To-Tr (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, V (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, Van Schaack, McGinnis vs. Sharpe (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, Wa-Welch (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, Wetherhead-Wh (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Court Case Records: Supreme Court of Judicature, Civil, Wi-Wo (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Court Case Records: Chancery, Annely vs. Lewis (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Court Case Records: Chancery, B (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Court Case Records: Chancery, Bailey vs. Buvelot (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Court Case Records: Chancery, Blouin vs. Wittmer (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Court Case Records: Chancery, Blouin vs. Wittmer (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Court Case Records: Chancery, C-D (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Court Case Records: Chancery, H-J (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Court Case Records: Chancery, Leadbetter vs. Harison et al (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Court Case Records: Chancery, Leadbetter vs. Harison et al (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Court Case Records: Chancery, Leadbetter vs. Harison et al (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Court Case Records: Chancery, M (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Court Case Records: Chancery, Pemberton (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Court Case Records: Chancery, R-S (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Court Case Records: Chancery, T-W (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Court Case Records: Chancery, Van Beverhoudt vs. Bayard (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Court Case Records: Chancery, Van Beverhoudt vs. Bayard (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Court Case Records: Chancery, Wittmer vs. Blouin (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Court Case Records: Vice-Admiralty, Criminal (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Court Case Records: Vice-Admiralty, Civil, A-R (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Court Case Records: Vice-Admiralty, Civil, S (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Court Case Records: General Sessions (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Court Case Records: Mayor and Alderman (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Court Case Records: Oyer and Terminer (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Court Case Records: Other Courts (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Court Case Records: New Jersey Courts (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Court Case Records: Governor and Council (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Court Case Records: Governor and Council (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Court Case Records: Governor and Council, Daniel Nimham (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Court Case Records: Court Undetermined, Criminal, A-H (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Court Case Records: Court Undetermined, Criminal, J-P (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Court Case Records: Court Undetermined, Criminal, R-W (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Court Case Records: Court Undetermined, Civil, A-D (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Court Case Records: Court Undetermined, Civil, E-H (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Court Case Records: Court Undetermined, Civil, J-N (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Court Case Records: Court Undetermined, Civil, P-Si (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Court Case Records: Court Undetermined, Civil, Sm-W (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Court Case Records: Case Undetermined, A-F (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Court Case Records: Case Undetermined, G-L (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Court Case Records: Case Undetermined, M (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Court Case Records: Case Undetermined, N-T (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Court Case Records: Case Undetermined, U-W (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Court Case Records: Case Undetermined, William Pride (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Court Case Records: Case Undetermined, Wills (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Court Case Records: Case Undetermined, Petitions (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Court Case Records: Case Undetermined, Lunacy Commission (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Court Case Records: Case Undetermined, Various/Fragments (Box 12, Folder 7)
- Series 2: Correspondence, 1730-1775 (bulk 1753-1774), and Undated, 1730-1775 and Undated
  - Subseries 1: John Tabor Kempe, Letters Received, 1759-1775 and Undated
    Arranged alphabetically by sender. This subseries contains letters to John Tabor Kempe regarding various court cases, especially land conflicts, and requests for assistance. Prisoners writing from jail often plead their cases to Kempe, and describe conditions in jail. A number of items deal with the disputed area of the New Hampshire land claims, and rioting there. Frequent correspondents include Rutger Bleecker, Henry Chase, Ann Cock, William Cockburn, John Duncan, Richard Dysart, Abraham Hausbrouck, Sarah Hayward, Whitehead Hicks, Harmanus Schuyler, Peter Silvester, George Spencer, Thomas Swords, John Wetherhead, and Abraham Yates. In addition, there are several letters from John Tabor Kempe's brother, William Kempe, asking for assistance, clothes, and money.
    - Correspondence: John Tabor Kempe, Letters Received, A-Blanchard, 1759-1775 and Undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence: John Tabor Kempe, Letters Received, Bleecker-Browne, 1759-1775 and Undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence: John Tabor Kempe, Letters Received, Ca-Cl, 1759-1775 and Undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence: John Tabor Kempe, Letters Received, Co, 1759-1775 and Undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence: John Tabor Kempe, Letters Received, Cr-Cy, 1759-1775 and Undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence: John Tabor Kempe, Letters Received, D, 1759-1775 and Undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence: John Tabor Kempe, Letters Received, E-G, 1759-1775 and Undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence: John Tabor Kempe, Letters Received, H, 1759-1775 and Undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence: John Tabor Kempe, Letters Received, I-K, 1759-1775 and Undated (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence: John Tabor Kempe, Letters Received, Kempe family, 1759-1775 and Undated (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence: John Tabor Kempe, Letters Received, L, 1759-1775 and Undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence: John Tabor Kempe, Letters Received, Ma-Mc, 1759-1775 and Undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence: John Tabor Kempe, Letters Received, Mi-Mu, 1759-1775 and Undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence: John Tabor Kempe, Letters Received, N-R, 1759-1775 and Undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence: John Tabor Kempe, Letters Received, Sa-Si, 1759-1775 and Undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence: John Tabor Kempe, Letters Received, Sk-Sw, 1759-1775 and Undated (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence: John Tabor Kempe, Letters Received, T, 1759-1775 and Undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence: John Tabor Kempe, Letters Received, V, 1759-1775 and Undated (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence: John Tabor Kempe, Letters Received, W-Y, 1759-1775 and Undated (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence: John Tabor Kempe, Letters Received, Unidentified, 1759-1775 and Undated (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Subseries 2: John Tabor Kempe, Letters Sent (Copies/Drafts), 1759-1775
    Arranged alphabetically by recipient. This subseries contains letters regarding court cases, land issues (especially in Albany County), and financial matters. Frequent correspondents include Rutger Bleecker, John Bradstreet, William Cockburn, Sir William Johnson, Harmanus Schuyler, and Thomas Swords. Letters to Sir William Johnson deal with the Crown's land disputes with Native Americans, and contain Kempe's opinions on the use of Native Americans as trial witnesses, the legitimacy of lan patents purchased from "the Natives," and the Daniel Nimham case.
    - Correspondence: John Tabor Kempe, Letters Sent, A-B, 1760-1775 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence: John Tabor Kempe, Letters Sent, C, 1760-1775 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence: John Tabor Kempe, Letters Sent, D-F, 1760-1775 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence: John Tabor Kempe, Letters Sent, G-J, 1760-1775 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence: John Tabor Kempe, Letters Sent, K-Q, 1760-1775 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence: John Tabor Kempe, Letters Sent, R-S, 1760-1775 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence: John Tabor Kempe, Letters Sent, T-Y, 1760-1775 (Box 15, Folder 6)